hi Mike how are you it's Frankie Freitas
how are you doing tonight yes fine and
yourself doing good doing good okay
why don't we start off by having you
tell people what this project that
you're interested in is about and how
you got interested in these holographic
Optical elements well
um this started in a strange way which
is really not so strange considering
that
it's understood that most of the
advancements of any particular field
come 95 percent of the as they say of
the advancements of any field come from
people outside of the field and that was
sort of my experience
what happened was
I was in the Solar field
and
I I was in Hawaii
and acting as a
[Music]
um
for PRI Pacific resources International
their commercial energy sales Division I
was considered to be an energy
management specialist
doe was having one of their last
uh evaluation and think tanks on these
large 30-foot diameter parabolic
dishes okay for a solar electric
generators constant they're sort of like
concentrators right yeah mostly front
surface mirrored systems yeah
um and
uh I was that was a very fascinating
um effort for me that was my first Think
Tank and I was really learning a lot I
was I was really awestruck by all of the
work done by groups mostly throughout
the U.S
um
and I I learned at some of these
meetings that well it's not my uh
position just to say oh wow these are
great but rather I'm supposed to look
for bugs
um the the objective was to try to find
what systems would work best in
different conditions and of course in
Hawaii
um the um the weather there is is
different than
um most other places in that
about every 20 minutes these high
vertical tropical clouds would go by and
it would disturb the performance of
these front surface mirrored parabolic
dishes that were used to concentrate
sunlight on a point
because the
clouds would cover up the mirror and
there would be a bright Cloud maybe over
to the right or the left yeah it would
it would basically diffuse the sunlight
yeah actually because they were
extremely high vertical tropical clouds
they would act as mirrors so the the sun
would be blocked out and the the uh the
disc of the parabolic disc would think
that the sun would be able to lighter or
the left and it would jockey over One
Direction or the other oh okay and uh
sometimes a a shadow would fall on the
dish and it would it would go into the
stove position thinking that it was
going to rain or something so these
dishes would work great out in the
desert in areas where there's not a lot
of clouds but they wouldn't pair very
well where the majority of the inhabited
population of the Earth were but anyway
um I realized that those systems would
work great in the desert but they
wouldn't find much use in areas where
the majority of the world's population
lives
now solar scientists have realized
um years prior to that that in most of
the inhabited areas that the majority of
the available energy
that
coming at these areas is in the diffuse
form
in the summertime there's a
a lot of direct
radiation but in the winter time it's
it's mostly cloudy
so most of these panels would work fine
in the summer but not so good in the
winter when you needed it okay so um I
uh I just asked the proverbial question
what if
what if we had some type of a
concentrator system that could gather
both the direct and the diffuse
components
and realizing that on an annual basis in
a lot of the populated area you can see
that the diffuse content is half or more
just over half in a lot of places
[Music]
so if you could come up with an optical
concentrator or a new magnifying glass
that could collect both then you really
essentially double the performance
of these collector apparatuses and and
hence you turned to uh holographic
Optical elements hoes well first um I
didn't know about hoes
um so I just did a
um
a rectilinear a geometrical Ray tracing
search if you uh to see if if it could
be done
and I just worked with a little 20 TI
scientific calculator and a pencil and a
ruler and a protractor and
um in a couple of weeks I came up with a
design and one of the guys on the think
tank was teaching Optical physics at the
University of Hawaii
um
I believe it's called
Manoa campus it just just up the hill
from Waikiki I think Steve Michael did
some holography work out in the out in
Hawaii as well but go ahead so
um I I asked him uh if he would check my
work to see if I was doing this right I
was just using smells law uh to do this
Ray tracing and he looked at it and he'd
uh
yeah
he just dropped his jaw and he he just
thought my goodness he thought this this
thing is so simple why why didn't we do
this before
and he we were in his office he had this
little uh not much more than a cubicle a
little little office at the University
there and he was just seemingly prancing
around saying gee he says I can see this
has laser application
and I looked at him dumbfoundedly and he
says this has fiber optic applications
and I said well I really don't know much
about that and he said he says well this
has applications and all transmitters
and receivers and I pull him well I
really don't know much about that I was
just trying to make a new magnifying
glass that could catch the diffuse
component
so he says well he said you showed me a
2d he says can you do it in 3D and I I
was showing him some of my work the
progression of my work and I flipped a
few more pages and I said well yeah it's
going to look something like this and he
said that's it
so I told him I said well let me finish
this drawing and I'll bring it back to
you and I'll show you
uh so I called him in a week or two and
I said well do you have time to see me
to take a look at this and he says oh
man he said do you have finances I've
been talking to my friends do they want
to talk to you and he says I took the
liberty to call doe and everybody's
excited and so forth so I went to see
him and um
he says well look he says they want you
to go back to the mainland
um so I did and I could be back to
Denver and I met with a fella Howard
Coleman that was head of the doe solar
thermals
solar thermal program and uh Howard said
look Mike he says we've got to look at
this and we realized what you've got he
said I want to introduce you to Larry
Shannon who was head of uh Carey and he
says Larry will walk you through this
and we really want to help you develop
this
but to make long story short what
happened was they found other
applications
and I was
um well they asked me to sign these
non-disclosure statements
and they gave you kind of a rough time
and what it was with people from DOD oh
I see so anyway at that time this was
the
days of FBI and Reagan Star Wars and and
so many things with with the name Optics
tag to it was Kept Secret for a while
until they could figure out what to do
with it I'm surprised the aliens didn't
have this technology already in their
spacecraft that they have
I'm just kidding go ahead
um
so anyway I uh I went on to other things
I I really wanted to know what they
meant about these other applications so
that encouraged me to I went out to
Pasadena City College and there's a
two-year program out there with Wayman
Lou well they used to have a laser
Electro Optics program and that's where
I took
um a couple of holography classes to
learn about hoes and and to realize that
this could be done by diffraction as
well as refractions
[Music]
um so
I
I did it the hard way if you will I I
spent it was like working on a puzzle I
spent
several hours each night to work with
lens design to to realize that Jesus
could be done by refraction and so like
thinking it all the way through it
helped me realize
in a rectilinear a geometrical way
um
uh the needed character or design of
optical systems
um which I guess is a little bit
different approach than
um
what a lot of folks in the field of
Optics
take what were some of the applications
that came out of this the Practical
applications in use
well
um
but of course
it's far as a multiplexer
and
um that would be for fiber optic
communication right yeah
well I guess it's it's you know I I
really couldn't name all the
applications my focus was on mostly
um solar and
um
I
I looked at a lot of domestic
applications now I remember reading
quite a while ago and I believe this
might have been through the University
of Pennsylvania
where they did some Greenhouse
experiment with hoe panels and
apparently if you were to stand in the
greenhouse even though the sun would be
transversing the sky
according to the plants and from the
plants perspective the sun always
remained overhead is is that fairly
accurate yeah that was a a Dr White
who set up three greenhouses one with
clear glass next one with a regular
frothy glass and the third with a
holographic
or hoe covered glasses and what they
realized was the plants with the clear
glass they do they grew tall and skinny
and the ones with the Cloudy glasses
they grew significantly better
they were more robust and not at all and
much more plant weight and all the good
things that you would like to see with
plants yeah they were more faux I
believe yes and they could be Harvest
more easily and the and the the ones
with the hose were even better than just
the Cloudy glass yeah they I think they
exhibited the qualities of both they
were they were they grew very tall but
they also grew very full yeah so
um
all right
what my objective with is with all of
this is to try to find
folks in the field of holography that
would be interested in
um kicking this back off again I just
let it lay for about 10 years
and I'm interested in I've done a little
project going right now the first of
this year I met
um
a well over the phone I met uh
Jack ludman and John Caulfield who were
working in a related area they
um attempted I don't know how far they
got but they attempted to start a
company called daylight savings which
uses the same uh principle I think John
ludman aced me to actually develop those
hoes for the greenhouse for uh Dr White
over at Penn State but uh what that's a
great company name daylight savings yeah
they think that there's going to be
lots of money involved with providing
appropriate daylighting in buildings
yeah there I I believe they're already
in use in architecture in different
areas uh yeah but it's not really
um
fully taken advantage of it's not a real
big effort these these guys are are
they've got some money backing or
they're supposed to anyway and and
they're hoping to start a big marketing
effort and
um provide I think they actually got a
contract with a university down in Waco
Texas to to put on
um maybe even hundreds of thousands of
square feet of these hoes to direct the
light in the appropriate Direction but
the problem is is that
um with a hookup path of solar or or
Windows in even on the east and west
side the light
um from the sun gets to be kind of
aggravating if people throw up curtains
now it would pass the solar what happens
is the it's sort of like driving West in
the afternoon and the sun is in your
eyes and it really uh throws a lot of
glare and it's it's it's not very
appealing it's not good for as they say
visual Acuity it's it's it's literally
harming your eyes you know consequently
people
um
um haven't
been really fully utilizing passive
solar
because of that so could you envision
this being placed within a car
windshield that would divert that direct
sunlight
uh yeah I I think not only
um
uh directing the light
um through the window but also uh
out of line of sight maybe
yeah and also maybe directing life
within the window
um
John Caulfield got a patent on
edge lighting for
um for Holograms
and um there's this law of reversibility
if you look at
um a as we see an optical train with
some lens system
um it it the input side
um the light will Traverse throughout
this this uh track of lenses and so
forth and come out at the output side
and if you throw it in light in the
exact opposite direction it will it will
end up where the input
or the infinite array um
was introduced this law reversibility so
um when John Caulfield came up with this
idea of these Edge lit or at least he
got the patent on the edge lit Holograms
um I realized right away we'll see this
could be used for solar hose to fiber
couple to bring the light down to
um wherever at the storage or immediate
use yeah this Edge lit technology was
that originally developed to illuminate
holographic
images those types of holograms or was
this more of a panel where you could
introduce the light source at the edge
and then have the panel actually radiate
that light outward well I think it was
used mostly for a holographic display
okay okay
yeah hmm
so I um I just realized that it could
also be used for for solar Holograms and
and uh transmitting the light down to
where you need it
now you're getting a lab set up to do
this if someone had a lab say uh amateur
hobbyist telegrapher they may have a
four by eight foot sand table you know
in their home or wherever it happens to
be how could they make a simple
holographic Optical element with a
helium neon laser in a simple setup for
demonstration purposes or just for
learning well
um
I the way I look at it is is
the direction that you want this lens or
this this hode to throw the light
is the direction at which you provide
lighting to expose the hologram
[Music]
so we need to be
being the reference beam and
an object beam and I imagine both of
those are sent to the holographic plate
and then the
degrading is created and is that then
used as the holographic Optical element
can you use that with white light or
does it have to be monochromatic laser
light as well in order for it to work uh
you mean to expose the Hologram Yeah
well yeah you need monochromatic to
expose it but once it's exposed
um is it is a laser transmission
hologram white light transmission
hologram you now happen to know what
steps would need to be taken well it's a
it's a transmission hologram yeah
um and um
you know I'm not really familiar with
the way John ludman set up his for Penn
State
but um I um I I believe that it it
should be done just as a um a regular
setup for transmission autograph yeah
just a regular split beam hologram but
instead of Illuminating an object to use
the object
[Music]
object of the holographic plate along
with the reference beam I would imagine
yeah
so what are your plans with this what
are you going to do with it well I've
got an application right now I'm putting
together a building with a passive solar
windows and um I I'm going to
cover the windows with these diffraction
gratings to throw the light up against
the ceiling
and do you have a website by the way uh
no I don't I I'm actually I'm I'm
putting together information
um and I I will shortly create a website
I do have an email address yeah I'm
going to make sure that I'm going to
make sure that your email address is on
the website so people listen to this if
they want to contact you they can send
you an email it's an interesting about
mac.com are you on a Mac yes I am
interesting yeah go ahead it's my name
it's Mike Engel it's uh h-i-n-g-l-e
mac.com okay now now if you look at this
this field of energy or solar energy
um uh what I used to teach these solar
classes down at Pasadena City College in
Tucson for three years and 90 91 and 92.
and also some energy classes for doe and
HUD a residential energy auditing and uh
what we used to talk about uh was the
magnitude of the problem if you look at
um
the energy our energy problem in the
world we realize that
um all the money that the world makes or
all your effort uh for sustaining life
if you will that 60 to 70 percent of
your cost of living goes to the energy
business
most people think well it's just my
electric bill and my gasoline bill but
um there's a hidden energy tax
in everything that we do and there's a
good example is say a cotton t-shirt
um if you look at the energy involved in
production producing that t-shirt you
have to plant the seed that takes energy
at the plow the field that takes energy
you have to
um yeah you have to fertilize and the
fertilizer has to be manufactured
through energy
[Music]
that's all mostly petroleum-based and it
takes energy to spread it you have to
irrigate that takes the energy you you
have to harvest the field and refine The
Cutting and transport it and uh then the
refined material you have to sew it
together and make clothes make the
T-shirt out of it and then the workers
drive back and forth and they put it in
a warehouse usually air conditioned and
then it goes into a store and people
drive to the store to pick it up and so
you can see that the majority of the
cost of that t-shirt is energy the the
cotton is just a little bit of seed
um that's very interesting yeah and that
goes with all goods and services
everything that you can that you look
around your room you see the majority
the cost as they say 60 to 70 percent of
everybody's cost of living the first
second and third world countries is
energy so it's a hidden tax it's energy
tax that's the world's biggest in
slavery if you will and that's why
there's so much
um tension if you will over uh petroleum
resources because
um the the world's economy is wrapped up
in energy yeah I did a hologram one time
with the solar panel
put it outside of the lab window here
and just fed it into one of the laser
diodes around the laser diode in the
middle of the day when the sun was
hitting the solar panel it just got free
energy to run the diode
I felt pretty neat about it that was
neat I like that well I think that we
can take it a lot further I I believe
that um you know if if you look at your
your end uses for energy it doesn't
matter if it's oil or gasoline or
natural gas or coal or nuclear or
whatever or so or you we we use it
really for we could say only three
purposes and um really four but you you
need light
you need heat or is it the opposite of
that is cool and you need shaft power
you know you're turning a mix or a
blender or maybe your uh your the wheels
in your car or something if you need
light heat and shaft power and then of
course there's communication
um and so uh the question is well can we
do this with photonics instead of
electronics and the answer is yes yeah
um
what's his name of Lauren the guy that
started the photonics Spectra back in
1954. oh not sure of the name
um Teddy Lauren I believe okay
um he wrote a neat statement and
sometime in the late 90s saying that the
um
the Workhorse that propelled us in the
20th century to this High
industrialization and uh
and Information Society was the electron
and in the decade and 90s we found that
virtually everything that we did with
the electron could be done better and
smaller and faster and much safer and
without interference or whatever with
the photons
and so they see that the 21st century
will be driven by photonics instead of
electronics
photons photons traveling through the
computer circuits instead of actual
electrons right Bell labs and IBM and I
I forgot who all but back and even I
think maybe the mid 80s was the first
Total photonics computers that this lab
models to to see if it would work
and um what's his name Schwarzkopf the
guy that headed up the Persian Gulf War
One
uh just days a couple of days after the
war was over he was in Congress saying
see what we did with this photonics
technology yeah so now we need more
money because we want to have a total
cotonics fighting force by the year
2000.
so you know hence there was a lot of uh
interest for military applications and
so a lot of the domestic applications
were hidden
but if you really think about it and
that's what I'm trying to encourage
people in this holography appeal to do
is to think about it is you can realize
that virtually everything we do for
lighting
for heating for cooking for
refrigeration for shaft power everything
we do with electronics we really can do
and even I believe simpler with
photonics I believe there are some
photonic stoves now am I correct with
that but I think they're based on
halogen technology but that's using
light to cook on
I'm not familiar with that I do know
that they're pretty they're fairly
pricey but I think they're out there
well what happens now with the cooking
for instance
you put a pot on the stove it's either
electric burner a gas burner typically
and um you cook some meal in it and
typically
um 95 of the heat of that cooking job
just goes out into the room yeah only
five percent actually gets put into the
food and so if you use
um
uh maybe a vacuum jacket and
um I use a on the the inside of this
vacuum if you use totally reflective and
and totally absorbing surfaces
uh then you might they would have like a
diode or a one-way mirror system so that
we can make sure that 95 of the heat
stays in the pot
and so this is actually being done
there's a group out of uh England
someplace that had one of these
30-minute TV commercials that showed
this uh looks like a pressure cooker
that what they do is it had some valve
on the top with an indicator that they
put um you know how they do they put
these meals maybe a roast with some
potatoes in there some greens and
whatever else they throw a whole bunch
of stuff in the pot and they brought the
in just a couple of minutes they brought
the pot up to some working temperature
and when some some indicator
showed that it was it was at the desired
temperature then they picked up the pot
with their bare hands
because it was vacuum jacketed and it
had these mirrored systems
and they put it in the The Ice Box okay
freezer and a couple of hours later they
pulled it out and everything was done to
perfection you know how they stir that
on TV yes yes okay so what that did was
they didn't show what it was but I knew
what it was because I had already been
doing some design of those type of
systems domestic systems showing that
yes we can do that what we've learned in
the field of Optics
especially in a lot of these critical
Navy space applications for a
cryogenically cooled sensors or whatever
that you need to employ that degree of
sophistication for
systems well anytime you increase
efficiency you also increase savings do
you think there's some sort of a
conspiracy going on that we're not
seeing these Technologies move more
rapidly well we need it for defense so
that we can beat the putting out of
these other countries for the remain in
oil
I see maybe that's where the other
things to be
um
of the situation but you know I think
that uh what we need to do is uh
um I think we're just too darn
comfortable and we don't have enough
people thinking in this direction
that the technology is there
and uh if we if we work together on this
we could really change the world we you
know I've seen the light I think we can
bring this out and uh change everything
for the better I've seen the light
that's that's a great way Mike we've run
up to 30 minutes I want to try and keep
it at 30 minutes so is there anything
you'd like to close things out with well
I would just like to see a team effort
and I would like to see
um talented people in this field come
together and to
um
set up a goal a project with a goal and
and to start develop
this technology domestic use of
photonics Technology okay
I want to thank you very much for coming
on the show boy thank you I'll have this
up probably over the holiday weekend and
send an announcement out and I'll make
sure that your downloadable documents
are there and also your email address
and anyone who would like to contact you
can do so great all right thank you Mike
I want to thank you very much for taking
the time to be on the show and I'll talk
to you soon okay
same to you bye
foreign